hello I'm your guest host Charlie
Chapman a developer Advocate at revat
and with me today is revat CEO Jacob
iding Our Guest today is David Barnard
you know him as the host of this very
fine podcast but he's also a longtime
Indie developer with his company
contrast and a growth Advocate and my
co-worker at Revenue cap on the podcast
we talk with David about the many
failures of his recent app launch the
surprising results of his first ever AB
test and the many reasons why you
shouldn't plan a big app launch all
right hello David welcome to your show
longtime host first time
caller that's great so I'm Charlie this
is David the longtime host of this
podcast First Time guest and with us as
well is Jacob iding my boss and CEO of
Revenue cat yeah I like the way you did
it in the pre-show which was and Jacob's
here too way to
Su yeah the reason I am in the host seat
and David's in the guest seat is because
David just released a really big update
to one of his apps and he has some
learnings to use a corpor phrase here I
guess to kind of share some things that
he learned as part of this launch
process and we thought it would be
interesting to sort of walk through that
and so I'm here to try and fill David's
shoes to walk us through that update so
and I think we're liberated Here Charlie
to be a little more direct than we
typically are with a guest that we've
invited and you know on good terms with
to bring on here but in this case
David's kind of a if he wants his show
back I think he's going to have
is this a hostile takeover well I don't
know you are sitting in the host chair
so I think I think you have squatter's
rights I'm an open book looking forward
to sharing whatever you want to ask
dangerous way to start this out before
we get into weather up 3.0 which is the
update that we want to talk about I want
to give everybody a primer of your
background as app developer not as
growth advocate of ricat so what is your
story as an IOS app developer leading up
to this weather up 3.0 launch I was a
struggling independent recording
engineer in 2008 and not seeing my wife
because I was working like 2: p.m. to 2:
am. and she was working 9:00 to5 and
when rumors of the iPhone SDK started
circulating which I saw because I was a
uber Mac nerd working in a recording
studio I started thinking hey this could
be a really good opportunity So within
days of Steve Jobs announcing the iPhone
SDK it wasn't even called iOS back then
and I started a company and I initially
intended to code all the apps and
started learning how to code and got
like three weeks into that and thought
to ship something in the summer I should
probably find a professional so I hired
a contractor and started building apps
and I've launched 20 something apps on
the App Store seen close to 10 million
downloads and millions of dollars in
Revenue so I've been at it a long long
time 16 years now starting from the
beginning you've gone through many
different business model iterations of
the App Store and I assume your apps
have as well yeah it's funny to me
talking to developers these days who
don't know the full history of the App
Store and the fact that Ina purchase
didn't even exist so early on we did all
sorts of crazy stuff like a popular
pattern for a long time was a free quote
unquote light version of the app kind of
what freemium exists today and it's
almost like your free trial and then you
push people to the paid version of the
app which was always HD right or was
that when the came along that was iPad
that was iPad all right yeah I guess a
little context for me too just so you
understand my weird references I came
into the iOS game a little later I
became an iOS Developer and started
building stuff in 2019 and I was
actually Android until like 2016 so I
learned most of my history through
podcasts like this before I was an
employee here so yeah most of that is
like me getting that secondhand as well
yeah then I did the whole like free
version with the ton of in app purchases
to like try and increase the average
revenue per user the craziest experiment
there I launched a timer app and it was
like 99 and it was doing fine and then I
relaunched it as a free app with a ton
of inapp purchases like oh you want this
theme it's 99 Cents you want that theme
and in the app was a quote unquote
ultimate bundle which I think was 10
bucks which at the time it seemed
totally ridiculous 10 bucks for a timer
out but people bought the freaking
ultimate bundle because they just wanted
everything and so I was making was a
better deal David you'd be stupid enough
to take the better deal you know it was
great and that was 2010 2011 or
something just experimenting with
business models and then I started
switching my apps to subscription in
2017 after Apple opened things up and
then I mean that's how I ended up at
Revenue cat and sub Club podcast and
everything else was trying to switch my
apps to subscription and it being such a
huge pain in the ass where we were
spending way more time on the
subscription app code and infrastructure
than we were building the products so
yeah so when did the first weather app
version like of those 20 apps you
remember like when you first were like
I'm going to do a weather app was it
your first weather app technically my
third weather app so perfect weather was
the first weather app I did but it was
like 2010 2011 so I've been building
weather apps for over a decade now and
then launched a whole brand new skew new
app as weather Atlas in 20 17ish and
then weather Atlas got rebranded as
weather up was weather L basically a
Rebrand then you said it was a new SK no
no no it was a new skew everything it
was just we wanted to switch to
subscription it was just such a brand
new take it's like file new project take
everything I learned from perfect
weather it was a new partner that's
another thing since I don't code I've
had this weird mix of working with
contractors that I pay and then some
combination of pay and do a REV share I
started doing the partnership thing back
in 2010 2011 after two projects went
sideways so each of those projects I
lost 50 Grand so I I was working with
developers they made all the promises in
the world but I was paying them hourly
and the projects just drug on and on and
on and I realized like these aren't
going to ship stopped throwing good
money after bad and I just wrote off
$100,000 that i' paid out that's when I
started thinking okay I need to work
with somebody who's got a little more
skin in the game yeah yeah yeah
developers without downside risk there's
nothing worse in the
world but then that has its own
challenges when somebody's working on as
a side project they can gets with their
jobs and so it's been a struggle too
working with that model so I don't want
to spend too much time on the history
but I think one other thing that is
probably related to the 3.0 launch for
weather up is what was your marketing
strategy for all these apps then you
presumably didn't have a huge
advertising budget or something at least
initially how has that sort of evolved
over time with all your apps yeah
depends on the app I've relied very
heavily on organic channels I've done
very little paid advertising early in
the App Store actually did spend
thousands of dollars trying to make it
work and like with paid apps it's just
was Total Money losing proposition but
mostly I've relied on getting attention
Apple's attention press attention and
then ASO has been really big for my apps
generally like launch Center Pro was the
top result for a bunch of like launcher
and other kind of terms so it got a lot
of browse traffic that's actually one of
the things that we'll get to with a
weather app trying to get any kind of
organic traffic those keywords are just
so C routed which makes it really hard
but one of my most successful apps was a
mirror app and go figure at its peak
something like 10 or 20,000 people
searched the app store for mirror every
day and I was capturing 68,000 of those
every single day ignorant person what
does a mirror app provide that like the
camera does
not so it's genuinely a good app and I
made it embarrassing I didn't imply it
wasn't David you
did one of the main things is that front
facing camera if you just launch the
camera app it's in a little window with
all the Chrome around it so this
launches to like a full screen mirror
you can zoom in we did some really cool
stuff like you tap a little flashlight
button and it puts white around the
edges of the screen and turns the
brightness up to 100% so that in dark or
lowlight situations it's actually really
helpful like one of those lighted
mirrors and stuff and then we had a
really cool way where you tap the screen
to like freeze the frame and then you
can save that as a photo so it's a kind
of cool way to preview your selfie
before you save it little things like
that but people love that app I guess it
becomes a thing you know to search for
right it's interesting the different
sort of niches will inform your strategy
like how you can acquire users I think
it's almost the opposite I think it's
like somebody's like I need to check to
see if my lipstick looks right and they
don't even think I can open the camera
app they're just like is there like a
mirror thing and then you know you just
search for it you're trying to solve a
problem and you go to the App Store if
the App Store is your default search
engine uh it can grab am creating that
Loop you know what I mean like
convincing people with normal human
people problems to look for software
let's just think about how magical that
is for a moment yeah I'm always
surprised when I look at my app figures
ASO Tab and see that I'm ranking well
and getting downloads from full
sentences like I want a green noise I
make a White Noise app a green noise for
free or something like that and it's
like people are just typing full-blown
search queries but yeah I asked that
because in the earlier era getting
attention if that's kind of your big
marketing strategy I don't necessar want
to say it's easier but it's definitely
different because like apple features in
the early it's way easier how many apps
are there now David like no Millions
there's millions and millions there were
like when I launched my first app there
were 270 apps on the App Store you
didn't need attention there were 270
apps on the App Store yeah yeah I guess
there's always people talk about
literally scrolling the list of apps
yeah you can look at
and by 2011 or 12 I mean it was
different but it still we were talking
probably in order of magnitude fewer
apps than there are today and it's still
to some degree like getting attention
especially in the early teens you know
2010 2011 12 13 was like the most
predictable thing you could do right and
to some degree it is and I think it's
probably one of the better more
predictable ways to like try to break
through the noise if you know how to do
it but yeah we should talk about it yeah
yeah especially if you have no marketing
budget so yeah let's talk about weather
up then and and like you mentioned
earlier weather up was a Rebrand of
weather Atlas you said and there's been
multiple versions of it over time so
when it came time to this weatherup 3.0
launch what was the state of weather up
at that time well I mean weather up 3.0
has been a long time in the making as I
mentioned you know working with a
partner my cousin he was busy with other
stuff and had a lot going on and so this
has been a very long slow started in
2019 actually like the designs for the
widget that's started doing apps yeah
actually yeah when I first opened xcode
for real what kind of kept happening was
we would get deep enough into one
specific feature and then just kind of
realized oh well to get attention we
really should be doing X and we finished
Y and I mean at this point I actually
regret not just shipping so like we were
pretty far
along watch app yeah just ship like we
should have shipped the Apple Watch app
in 2020 probably when that was ready but
that was when widgets got really big and
so like now we got to build a widget so
at wwc
2020 we're like okay we got to build a
widget we can't just launch the Apple
Watch app then we're so close to
launching the widget and then Apple
announced interactive widgets and it's
like we can't just launch a widget when
everybody else is launching interactive
widgets and so we should have just
launched but we held off the tough thing
about getting attention is that you do
have to do something unique well widgets
were really cool and unique in 2020 when
they first were home screen widgets but
2021 that's not enough to get attention
Apple watch apps complications like all
these things and that's a trade-off the
calculus for me was well let's wait and
try and make a big splash with all these
things but really like at this point we
could have already had launched the
widget and just adding interaction at
the level we did would have gotten
attention you'd be on weather up 7.0
yeah exactly so presumably then that
long an amount of time without major new
features was impacting the business then
or were downloads pretty much just
swimming along yeah I mean that's one of
the big regrets I was actually just
looking at app figures recently and
downloads were pretty consistently good
and we had some nice spikes from getting
attention or being part of big launches
with new iOS features and stuff like
that all the way up until about 2019
when things went on Hiatus and we were
working towards this bigger update and
things really dropped off the map like
apple stopped featuring the app because
it hadn't been updated in a while we
stopped getting any kind of bumps from
these new updates and things like that
so coming into the weather up 3.0 I mean
it's almost like launching a whole new
app because downloads were at low double
digits a day like 15 downloads a day I
mean I guess for some IND the apps
that's a lot but it's hard to build a
business and make any money on that so
the revenue was down I've actually been
losing money on the app for like 18
months I've been funding it out of my in
the future DAV investing in the future
yes and again I think that was one of
the mistakes and that's the beauty of
subscription apps too is that except for
the getting attention there's no
incentive to hold back features like
launching a big 3.0 where you're doing a
paid update where everybody's paying you
for the features well nobody was going
to pay me any more because I launched
those features so I should have just
launched them and kept moving yeah
because even a really massive big
splashy launch amortized over the time
between big launches that time in
between big launches is arguably a lot
more important than how splashy the
launch itself is unless you're just
starting out that's where it can make a
really big difference to start from a
big stepping stone I think the big
launch philosophy has been one of like
the great mistakes of my career there's
so many incentives to be like oh yeah
we're just going to roll this together
into a big thing or like we're going to
put this all together in the fall you're
honestly justifying not shipping right
you're being like I'm not lazy or I'm
not scared a strategy right and it's
like yeah for me it's definitely fear
right is like oh I don't want to like
I'm not going to show this to the world
because I need this one little extra
thing otherwise people are going to
ignore me I do think it's a legacy of
box software really though the mindset
and it did work prior to subscriptions
when especially paid upfront apps it
works really well like launching a pro
would get massive spikes in Revenue
where it'd make like 60k in a week they
we'd go along making you know hundreds
of dollars a day hundreds of dollars a
day and then we'd have another big
launch and then we'd go up but I mean
why is it even called weather up 3.0 3.0
it's like yeah and prior to that mindset
so I think a bit too it was like all
about building and packaging these big
updates and then talking about
leveraging that into love from Apple and
the Press right so there were like a
bunch of these compounding things but I
think you're right that if you
reamortize that over the time value
delivered right those features that you
withheld for months are not compounding
or four years or whatever are not
compounding over that period And I think
it's really easy for that to overcome
and then of course there's always I
think just the psychosocial aspect of it
is that if you're not shipping you're
not shipping and if you're not shipping
every day you're not shipping your
probability of never shipping goes up
yeah right yeah I think we're especially
in the sort of Apple sphere I think a
lot of us have a tendency to think of
our marketing like Apple's marketing and
it's like Tim Cook can sneeze and that
can be like news story we are not that
and so do you have a Phil Shiller you
should get one then you could be apple
but you don't have a Phil Shiller right
like Apple's marketing is world class
and they're professional right and it's
not just buil decades and decades and
Decades of yeah they know the cadences
they know how to control the narrative
they know how you know what I mean and
and they are doing paid updates though
that's the thing it's like a lot of
their launches are convincing you to get
a new iPhone and so it is like save it
up save it up save it up and then do a
big Hardware to do it yeah and when it
was box software that was part of the
deal you had to hold back those features
and early in the App Store you would
release a new skew as a paid update
because there was no way to monetize
that user base over time I think a lot
of what y'all were just saying I keep
thinking yes because subscription
business model allows you to acrw that
value over time and make it compound
versus the old model of paid apps and
paid updates didn't allow you to do that
point taken like nobody cares about
those things anymore and so don't hold
off on shipping and that was a mistake I
made was for the last four years kind of
getting dropped in that old mindset that
did work in the past for me but no
longer works in the same way because
that's not how I run my business I think
each small update is an opportunity to
reach for attention and maybe not like
send an email to your press contact or
whatever because that you can
oversaturate but if you're constantly
making small updates and each time you
can make a little video or something of
that update every single one of those is
a chance to catch somebody news
attention and oftentimes what they're
going to see is an old feature that just
happens to be part of your demo you're
like cashing in on an old feature or
something each one of those times like
most people aren't getting tired of you
Tweeting too often because most people
don't see it in the first place and then
like you said earlier one of you two is
if you're constantly tweeting to the
point of almost being annoying it also
kind of signals I get this with Revenue
cat stuff you guys are pushing so much
stuff out I can barely keep up which
kind of shows that like I'm on top of
things we're constantly coming out with
new stuff even if you don't use it that
signal adds value perceive value anyway
to your product and for a weather app
like this I mean I'm sure a lot of it's
the mass Market but for getting a start
for getting anything written about it or
whatever you have to at least like
appeal to The Connoisseur of apps right
and somebody's going to check how many
updates there were and
like so yeah let's get to the actual
launch itself then so what was your I
guess strategy going into that launch we
already talked about the actual update
it was interactive widgets and a watch
app right but what was your plan for
getting attention press and you know
hoping to get featured by Apple we'll
get into mistakes but I kind of did the
same Playbook I have for years was I
know if I do something Innovative I can
get some attention for that Innovation
and then typically when you do something
really Innovative with a feature like
interactive widgets that Apple has been
really pushing heavily and was a big new
kind of part of the OS update you can
get attention so my goal for the launch
was to get as much attention as I could
from press from Apple from others make
some money and then take that and start
experimenting with apple search ads and
then if that went well start expanding
marketing beyond that but that's not how
things went which we'll get to yeah how
are you trying to get that attention I
know you most people listening know you
you have a lot of contacts what was your
general strategy to try and get those
press articles and apple features people
say oh well you know people and that's
how you get featured but I don't think
that's totally true it helps they will
at least scan my email or at least see
that I DM them and maybe I have like a
tiny bit of faked in credibility because
they know me or have know me for a while
or whatever but at the end of the day
and I think about this all the time is
that I'm not actually going to capture
their attention unless I do something
that they care about and so for me
thinking about reaching out to all my
press contacts I would be embarrassed to
send them weather up 3.0.1 update with
like one tiny little feature that's not
even interesting I still feel a ton of
pressure to do something that's actually
interesting in the market that they're
going to be willing to write about
because I'm not going to push somebody
to write about something that's not
actually interesting and that's where
for this particular update I worked on a
video that demonstrated the features
funny enough Jake Moore who we've had on
the podcast a ton and done a ton stuff
with the CEO of super wall has been
talking about for years how impactful
videos are for pay walls and with this
interactive widget it felt like it just
something so visual that it needed a
video so I was working on the video for
the pay wall primarily and it turned out
so good that ended up being my press
pitch so instead of hundreds of words I
mean you just have so little time to
capture somebody's attention so the main
way I pitched it was like a DM on
Twitter and like hey I'm working on some
really cool interactivity for widget
some weather I think this is really
interesting and I got quite a few people
who are like yeah I don't really cover
apps anymore or you know I wouldn't Ty
cover an
app but they saw the video we're like
wow that looks really cool so I think
whether or not you have a relationship
with somebody because a lot of people I
pitched I didn't know and they didn't
know me but it's all about communicating
that value and it being something that's
actually worth them writing about and
that video like really helped yeah cuz
it's not just value to the user it's
also interest for a story which are
slightly different things you got to
help them get their story written for
the week right like they have a job they
have a quota they have a number thing
you have to produce and if you want them
help them do their job and find
something mutually beneficial for all
three parties right the reader the
journalist and you if I was to say any
sort of distillation of how to do PR
it's that like build something that's
mut like win to all parties and it's
hard you have to find something they
interest in right you read about what
they do you learn about you know
whatever well I mean this is February of
2024 which like every Tech and other
wise online outlet in journalism is
disappearing right now like on the daily
so maybe like the last one to get this
in before writing about apps just
doesn't exist anymore if you needed any
more signs that this model of launching
is no longer like that might be it to
that same point it's not just is it
interesting but is it interesting
currently you had a little bit of an
uphill battle well you had a huge uphill
battle which we'll get into a second but
even ignoring what happened on your
launch day you weren't launching this
when iOS 17 was coming out with these
interactive widgets where huge regret
people in the Press were literally
begging please send me your interactive
wig need some I need something ship
about and I don't want to just copy
Apple's press release right you had to
pitch them on it in was this January
when you were starting to kind of reach
out yeah yeah so like not only did you
need it to be compelling in its own
write as a story that they already want
to write but you had to make them want
to write it well after the readers are
demanding this anyway let's move to the
actual launch because this is where
things get pretty interesting so I guess
I'll just let you take it away but how
was your launch day itself
terrible really really bad at least you
didn't at least you didn't wait four
years for it so that's good yeah I know
after four years a hard work of all the
things to happen I had scheduled the
launch put it on my press page so if you
go to press. contrast. we'll link it in
the show notes but I create a press page
for every release that I'm trying to get
a little press for and on there I put
the launch date and time so it's kind of
the Embargo time so I did talk to a few
journalists and I had set this time and
it turned out that at the exact same
moment Apple was planning on announcing
their dma compliance and so somebody
from the Press reached out and said hey
there's big news coming an hour from now
can I just publish now and I was like oh
shoot not good it's like all right just
go for it then I reached out to other
folks that I thought might be writing
about it and told them like go ahead and
and write about it and then even like
9o5 mac was like hey I think we should
just wait till tomorrow they didn't even
publish till the next day and then
several of the people I was talking to
got so distracted with the dma news that
they didn't even write about it so there
was like layers there of one it didn't
get written about by as many outlets as
would have likely written about it had
it not then two there wasn't any kind of
like social Halo because the eror got
sucked out of the room so people who may
have seen it and may have otherwise
tweeted about it or said hey this is
cool or other journalists see Tech
crunch write about it and they write
their own story instead everybody was
like super busy I didn't even know you
watch that day David to be honest like I
was so busy like I think on a normal day
I was going to say even including you
David like people on that day you are
one of the people that people go to
Twitter or whatever to find so it's like
they go to your Twitter and they might
see like hey I launched this new thing
and they're just scrolling to find your
take on this new thing because this is
why I don't discourage side apps
explicitly because the world just
discourages side hustles all like your
main gig will always destroy anything
you try to do yeah so like an hour into
my app launch and I didn't know what the
news would be but an hour into the
launch before I even had a chance to
like tweet it from the company account
before even some of my own launch Day
plans were finished Apple announced that
and then I was like all hands on deck
with you and Jacob and everybody else at
Revenue cat trying to figure it out and
then scheduling a webinar for the very
next day and like reading through all
the documents and chatting about it
internally and so what would have maybe
otherwise been a lighter Revenue cat day
where I take a little personal time to
celebrate my app launch was just
completely so it said I was up till like
2: a.m. reading the fine print of
European regulation to host a webinar
the very next day it was just about as
big of a disaster as you could possibly
have when your plan is to get attention
Apple still hasn't featured and I'm not
totally sure why but I have a feeling
it's that well two things and this is a
regret that I have now looking back is I
was trying to squeeze it in ahead of
Vision Pro and I thought so much air was
going to get sucked out out of the room
from Vision Pro what I didn't know was
Apple was distracted with the dma but
the whole editorial team was I'm sure so
busy with the launch of the Vision Pro I
never could have known that the dma
would be such a big deal and would be
launched on that day but I should have
known that the App Store editorial team
would be super busy with the Vision Pro
and the reason I was trying to get it
out was to launch was to like actually
ship versus like oh now we need to build
a Vision Pro app before we can ship and
so I was trying to get out before the
Vision Pro so that people weren't asking
where's your Vision Pro app or whatever
Well turns out a month later I don't
think anybody would ask for a Vision Pro
up anyway so hindsight 2020 I should
have just waited a month and let the
Vision Pro stuff blow over before
launching but that's a top tip sub Club
listeners if you're going to launch your
app don't do it on the day that Apple
announces the dma so take that one write
that one down in your notbook this is
really actionable this applies to all
businesses you do better if Pi a
different day than the day that the App
Store melts down in Europe but it's
another side effect of the big launch if
you put all your eggs into one big
launch basket you're sometimes you're
just going to catch a stray some big
news article is going to come out it
happens with fundraisings too like
companies put big like efforts behind
their fundraising announcement and then
that morning whatever Company files for
bankruptcy and the entire like startup
news Escape is like covered with that
right nobody cares or some other company
raises more or whatever that's just a
risk and there's sometimes a little bit
you can do to like drisk that maybe you
have a friendly contact in the press
that tells you hey there's already an
embargo news drop that day but like
you're not usually that lucky but if
you're launching more often you have a
more even you know you're drisking your
launch Plans by having many small
launches you could always try to do both
right why can't you just have many small
launches and big launch too right I
think you can kind of no and that that's
what I should have done I could have
done that we could have launched the
Apple Watch app and it would have been
just launch it
Qui and then be like this is weather of
three they've never seen it these
journalists have never seen it like you
can that's what I was going to say
you're saying the big launch and I think
big launch maybe has two meanings
there's like the big launch in the sense
of you're holding a bunch of stuff for
this one big launch but there's also the
meaning of like making your launch big
like going for just being loud and
everything and you can be loud once a
month I mean this is the YC advice if
you have a launch that goes poorly Just
Launch again the definition of a bad
launch is nobody sees it so nobody's
going to see you do it again right
Revenue cat do that I think you said
that stage somewhere so I think we
posted on Reddit and it kind of got some
steam and then we launched a beta like
every time we fundraise we're like
Revenue cats launching out of we make
some stuff up and it's a little bit of a
wink and a not like we're always doing
stuff right yeah I guess it's a little
bit of Showmanship just to like put a
narrative to the building you've been
doing and you can kind of do I mean look
at Tesla like every Big company juices
up stuff they've been working you know
they dress it up they push it that's
what marketing I me every Apple keynote
starts with a bunch of things that sound
like launches is that only all the super
nerds are like we've heard this before
right but most people watching it are
like this is new like this is okay who
are watching which is probably who it's
for but yeah I mean it's the power of
narrative control right like you can
really kind of Drive The Narrative and I
always telling you guys before to start
the podcast this is all made up
everybody has all it's made up you can
just contrast is made up but yeah
nothing you can do to control for like
just dumb luck and it feels like in this
particular case kind of the mistake if
you were to say that would be you made a
lot ride on this single event and then
things that are outside of your control
can go wrong and you gave up on all of
the smaller events that could have
happened over the last three years or
whatever and put it all into kind of all
your Quivers behind or I don't know the
phrase something with a bow and arrow
and putting everything behind the one
bow or Arrow all my eggs in one basket
and so that maybe is like the mistake
that happened here but I guess maybe the
more interesting thing then is what now
what are you going to do are you going
to do like Jacob said are you going to
try and relaunch short answer yes I
wanted to actually go through more of
the failures of launch and to give the
audience a little bit of context Jacob
and I were chatting Friday and I was
like we were talking about the podcast
broadly and we've had some really great
guests on but one of the things I want
to do more is talk to people who have
failed and talk about even the ones who
have succeeded about all the failures
leading up to the success and I was like
yeah I failed so bad with weather app
and jaob was like well let's talk about
it if we're going to get other people on
the podcast to talk about failures why
don't you lead by example and so this is
Monday like three days later and that's
exactly what we're doing so I actually
want to talk through more of the things
I think really failed at the launch
before we get to like how I hope to
potentially recover from this failed
launch because I think it's really
instructive and then for me doing all
this stuff it informs the questions I
ask on the podcast you I'm using Revenue
cat experiments in the app it informs
how I talked to my colleagues about our
product internally I give tons of advice
on sub Club I get tons of advice on sub
club didn't take all the
advice I think one of the other big
failures I wanted to discuss was pricing
and specifically because we talked so
much about pricing and I kind of just
failed at every level of the like
typical advice that we give so one of
them is pricing is not as important as
you might think and it's probably better
to launch with a lower price and just
get more people using the app and get
more subscribers and I launched with
what is probably the highest ticket
weather app subscription at $4 a month
was fine but the $40 a year but
interestingly my biggest regret is not
the $40 a year is that I didn't do a
sale on launch so this is the advice I
would have if you are going to do a big
attention grabbing thing do it with some
kind of a discount 25% off 50% off
whatever because all that attention I
did get most of the people who wrote
about it listed the price a lot of
people who maybe even read the tech
crunch article read it on 9 to5 Mac
Reddit on Mac Rumors or whatever boy
Genius report they all saw $40 and were
like no way but if they had seen $40 but
H 50% off I think we would have better
it creates like that urgency like take
action now don't just wait part of the
reason I wanted to push the envelope is
I talked to so many folks here on this
podcast and we talked to so many people
inside Revenue cat where they have what
seem like unreasonably high prices in my
theory now is that well one this is a
weather app it's a commodity good I
should have really better understood
like willingness to pay I should have
looked at what other apps are charging
and everything but the other thing is
like the source of attention matters a
lot so the apps that are charging a
higher rate they're either creating a
lot of demand through paid advertising
where there's not a lot of expectation
going into it versus getting pressed
like the attention you get I think makes
a difference to that willingness to pay
and the type of people you attract and
then especially apps that are really big
with search if somebody's searching for
a weather app and is like looking for a
solution that's a really different
audience than people just seeing it in
the press and wanting to check it out so
there's like a different kind of intent
a different kind of user all those
things and so I think it was a move
pricing it at 40 bucks I think we
probably should have done 30 and then
done a discount to1 1999 for the launch
yeah it's interesting almost definitely
this thought is coming from me listening
to this podcast but like the idea that
the journey that the users taken at the
point when they see the pay wall being
super important which oftentimes is when
you're talking about the onboarding
experience but it's also the attribution
as well it's interesting to think that
yeah like whether that person came
through a splashy launch or press versus
the high intent they were searching for
it or they saw an ad on Facebook or
whatever that should also Drive what
offering you're sort of showing them on
that pay wall I don't know if I've ever
seen this before but it would be
interesting to oh I guess I have on a
launch itself all the Press people that
you're trying to get to write an article
include a link that has the attributions
so that that discount only applies if
they get it through their article if
you're launching an otherwise Unknown
app with a press you can pretty much
guarantee anybody who buys it on that
day is coming from the Press right do a
Time limited sale even if 100% of users
that's the case from the person writing
the article story them being able to say
N9 to five readers are the only well
yeah that's true you could just say that
um am I coming off unscrupulous nobody's
nobody's gonna mind it's literally true
if they click they'll get the discount
maybe everybody else gets a discount too
but I think that's something that could
live on though right like one of the
things
for me that I do see in the data and
also it's in my head that this is a
thing is like a lot of these journalists
for some of the bigger press junkets
they spend a lot of time on SEO they
make these big listicles because they
know that one they'll get a lot of
attention on that day but then they'll
get attention for the next six months
when somebody buys their new iPhone and
they're like all right what are these
new widgets because that's probably when
they actually update their phone at the
same time that's a driver of traffic
overtime for your app as well each one
of these articles that they write that
deal kind of can live there as well
that's also part of that narrative
that's user Journey all the way to your
pay wall so like theoretically those
could even live on there and show a
different offering to somebody that came
from an article versus somebody who came
from searching I need to know the
weather or whatever in the App Store one
other thing I do want to mention on
pricing is that I priced based on things
that I knew and based on my thinking of
the value of weather up and my costs in
servicing weather up not on the customer
perceived value of weather up and I
think that's a huge thing that Founders
can get themselves tied up in kns about
and I succumb to it myself is that one
of the features that we were leading
with that I don't think many people are
even using people didn't even talk about
it much but I was personally so excited
about it because this is how I use it is
that with weather up 3.0 you can set a
different weather Source per widget and
so I have a whole home screen dedicated
on my iPhone with three widgets and it's
Apple weather as a source airs weather
as a source and ACU weather as a source
so at a glance I can see whether any of
the forecasts are showing rain coming I
can see the differences in the forecast
and everything like that super uber
nerdy feature well it's also very
expensive to do that because every 15
minutes or whatever it's hitting the
server not one time to one weather data
provider and the weather data is why had
been losing money on the app leading up
to this launch was that it's just really
expensive to provide weather data and
then widgets and complications are
especially expensive because they're
constantly updating in the background so
I got myself all twisted in knots
thinking okay we need to make sure
there's a level of profitability here
and if a bunch of people start putting
five widgets on their home screen with
different locations at different sources
and everything else it's going to get
really expensive for us to service these
customers it's really hard to educate
customers on how expensive weather data
is and then the fact that it's even more
expensive because it's WEA man like I
don't don't tell me about your business
model I don't want to know and so I was
pricing based on my knowledge of that
and my own like thinking the feature was
going to get super hyped and you only
have the one tier right it's not like
you have a more expensive plan M exct so
you had to model it in like some
percentage of users are going to be
doing all of this yeah exactly I'll call
back I don't think we talked about you
didn't put any product analytics two
causes of death there but one you didn't
have product analytics to tell you how
many users are doing this which you can
probably look at the API calls to see
like the relative now you know the
percentag is which then I'm going to
bust you for that's another symptom of
not launching if you had launched this
as it Standalone thing you could have
like not touched anything just measured
how many people are doing what and then
you would have some idea of like okay
actually as long as we charge X we're
going to be able to cover cost because
not that many people actually use this
feature there's some risk there but yeah
and this is why we talk talk about all
this stuff like I should have surveyed
some users I should have value based
pricing value based pricing is typically
helpful I think actually in this case
David value based pricing is hurtful for
your bottom line potentially actually
not because I think if you're closer to
the perceived value of the product
you'll get a better Optimum in value
based pricing you want to set your
pricing to the perceived value for some
aggregative users as opposed to cost
based pricing where you're saying it
cost me X dollar to deliver I'm going to
charge X Plus 5% profit or whatever in
SASS and stuff it's really important
because the cost to Del is often very
very low if you cost price just to your
cost you're giving away too much and
often especially in SAS where you're
like as a developer having to ask for
$100,000 a year right you really have to
be like gosh that's so much money for
software but then you go like well if
I'm replacing a developer or if I'm
replacing some amount of headcount or
some amount of whatever now I see the
value right the value is there and
therefore you know you can feel it but
you could be on either side of that
price curve in the sense that like
you're pricing way above the perceived
value the demand's going to drop off
again so value based pricing doesn't
necessarily mean charge more it just
means like charge the perceived value
because the costs are only something
really the provider of the service cares
about well they're highly variable based
on the number of users which is weird
too yeah and and also like at the stage
like there's some fundamental costs that
you can never get below potentially but
like you should really I mean when
Revenue cat launched like our cost
structures were really brutal in the
early days right but it was like it's
okay because eventually we're going to
have a team that's going to focus on
making everything offici efficient and
driving down costs and whatever but the
early days it was just like turn up the
database dial right like just keep mning
money um but obviously a different thing
where you apis you have more fixed cost
but I think the worst way to do this is
to be like how much did it cost me to
build this yeah and then they divide
into that it's like no don't do that
don't do that that's not going to end
well for you and then the bigger problem
for me too was on the value based
pricing front is that people have
expectations coming in to a weather app
like understanding my market
as weather nerds like who's going to put
this widget on their home screen weather
nerds weather nerds already have five
other weather apps they're probably
subscribed to two other weather apps so
they have a sense of like what a weather
app should cost and one of the ones I
got compared to which I know Brian the
developer of carrot weather and that's
one I got called out against was like
well carrot weather has more features
and is only $30 a year on their like
most premium tier and it's true if I
would have thought more about who I
would marketing too I would have
realized that they already have that
price comparison in mind and yeah it's a
real thing to assume the market is
already somewhat in equilibrium
especially for something where you have
a lot of products I don't think looking
at your competitors you know if you're
building something truly new it's harder
but if you're building something that's
like I want to say a commodity but think
of car companies like car companies are
super precise in their pricing right
because most cars are Commodities right
there's like slightly differentiated and
so they have to be laser tight with
where the market is and they know they
won't sell them if there cost more than
this and stuff like that yeah and you
got to price in that differentiation too
right I think that was a little bit of
where I was hoping that this would
differentiated enough and valuable
enough we got thousands of subscribers
at this launch it wasn't a complete
failure so I mean it did kind of prove
that a certain number of people were
willing to pay a premium for what they
perceived to be a premium feature and a
premium experience now I have the
opportunity experiment you had asked
earlier about you know where do I go
from here and we kind of already covered
it is like I'm going to launch again am
I going to get as much press this time
probably no but like you said I'm going
to create one or two features nothing
massive but one or two features that I
think are interesting enough to get some
more attention and bundle those up and
do a little relaunch and some people
will be seeing it for the first time and
I'm going to put it on sale exactly
exactly and then from there then I can
like experiment more with pricing and
win back offers and things like that so
you I want to shill here for a minute
cuz you you used a bunch of Revenue cat
stuff right you ran into some
experiments things how did that stuff go
cuz like that's probably more than most
folks do on a launch but I'm what did
you set up what did you use and like how
did that go yeah I mean I guess as a
guest I get to shill rubby I want an
honest customer
testimonial pay walls went way better
than I expected so we used the revenue
cat footer viw where we built a custom
Swift UI pay wall behind where we're
able to do the video do a lot of like
custom fancy stuff which probably
wouldn't have made that much more money
we' have just used one of the revenue
cat templates but I wanted to do the
video on the playall and everything else
but it was really nice being able to let
Revan cat just do all the logic behind
purchases and everything else so it
saved us a ton of time I think Brock who
did the development I think he said the
super fancy Swift UI pay wall took like
less than a day and then all the like
logic and everything else for context if
people don't know like we have a pay
walls feature at Revenue cat where we
can render everything for you and it's
all driven by the back end you can
change things but there's a version of
it where the only UI we render is the
actual hard part which is the prices and
the CTA at the bottom and that stuff and
then you can build your own Super
customized fancy animated marketing view
behind it and so that's what you it's a
great solution for the developer that
wants to like still own the pay wall but
you also want to save a bunch of time
well in selfishly from our perspective
it also means that we do support any
bespoke feature that we haven't built
yet ourselves into our so like at the
beginning we didn't have like videos or
if you have certain types of slideshows
even if it's not super complicated if we
haven't built it yet it is possible I
don't think he had to do anything Brock
codewise because once we were using Pay
walls to power it I was able to kick off
an experiment so at launch I scheduled
it which that's a new feature scheduling
experiments but I scheduled the
experiment to start like midnight the
day of launch or or 12:01 a.m. the day
of launch and the experiment I launched
with and it was so fascinating because
Revenue cat shipped experiments 18
months two years ago and I've talked to
people who've launched experiments
Charlie you wrote a blog post about
using experiments like a lot of people
have talked about experiments but
launching an experiment that I conceived
of implementing it myself it was just
such a different experience of like dog
fooding Revenue C and then also again
podcast and the advice I give and what
experiments to run and all those kind of
things it was so fascinating to set up
an experiment myself run it look at the
results analyze the results real skin in
the game too right it's easy to talk
about somebody else's decisions and
tests and be like oh you should do blah
blah that's all I do all day but yeah
when it's your money and you're like I'm
actually testing this it's different yep
so it just work though that's pretty
cool like which it should I say unless
you're putting something embedded in the
behind the footer view in the like
custom view like the footer will just
automatically adapt to the offering even
just customizing a pay wall for having
two different offerings pre without
using stuff which just it's not
insurmountable but it's days of drudge
you know so this is the first AB test
I've ever run in 16 years of building
apps because it was always such a hassle
I didn't want to pay for SAS to run AB
test I didn't want the developer to
spend months building out some bespoke
system so the only way I've tested in
the past which we talk about this on the
podcast I think it's a valid way to test
is you launch and you look at the
numbers and then a week later you you
update the app with something very
different and then you look at the
numbers that week and that's a valid way
to do it but this is the first time I've
ever done a real AB test because it was
so easy to do and so the test I did was
defaulting to annual being the
pre-selected option on the pay wall
versus monthly being the pre-selected
option on the subtle so it wasn't even
like different price you were just like
subtle ux difference which you can test
with Revenue C pay
W so just what's the default and part of
the reason I did that is that I was
considering just making the monthly the
default always because we've talked to
folks here on the podcast about how
monthly shortens that feedback loop of
like people who are staying engaged with
the app and turning quickly and
everything like that and then I also
wanted to get some monthly recurring
Revenue built up because we have monthly
recurring costs and so do we do a big
launch where we get a bunch of annual
and then we need to budget that over
time to make sure that we can keep the
weather API bill paid or do we try and
get more month Revenue where it's like
more consistent over time so the results
were fascinating and I'm looking at the
results right now but the headline is
that realized LTV less than a month in
so I don't have renewals yet on the
first renewal month but realized LTV is
60% lower on the people who saw monthly
that makes sense because a lot of the
people who saw monthly just stuck with
monthly but I was running some numbers
with my colleague Dan and this is
something it would be really fun for us
to model at some point but you know
assuming a normal level of churn I'm
unlikely for the realized LTB to cross
before the year mark and then at the
year mark those annual renewals will
kick in and the realized LTV will shoot
back up again and so basically I just
made less money by launching with this
well no you learn you learned about
something that definitely doesn't work
right like you mapped out the probably
does I think the I think the interesting
thing here is when you stop this
experiment you'll still be able to track
these cohorts for the next I think 400
days or something I would go back and
look at these results after that year
mark when your annuals have actually
started renewing and then look at your
actual lifetime value not over 30 days
but over that full period yeah 366 day
of lifetime value instead of just yeah
the first because that's something that
like you can make a lot of inferences
based on other people you know what
their annual turn rate looks like versus
monthly but at the end of the day you
don't really know until you see what
yours looks like yeah the monthly
renewals will start coming in this
Thursday actually and so I'll be able to
see pretty quickly but in Revenue
cat.com you can go into the subscriber
retention and see the number or
percentage of people who have turned off
auto renew already and so I already know
that my turn in this first month is
already going to be above 30% so I'm
going to retain somewhere around 70% of
users like not higher because 30% have
already turned off auto renew and so by
looking at that I already kind of know
I'm going to retain probably less than
70% and so then you run some quick math
on like even as that turn declines over
time because month two it'll hopefully
be less and month three it'll be less
and less like fewer and fewer users
return and more people stick around but
like the Math's not looking good for
those two lines to cross I David so just
pre-selecting drove that much difference
in Behavior like how many people on the
a still ended up buying monthly like did
it make a significant difference yeah
okay so here are the numbers I'll round
them up to just make it easy for
listeners since we're not going to like
have a screen share or anything of the
people who saw the annual as a default
around 800 of them went with annual but
almost 400 selected monthly so a lot of
people who saw annual did switch to
monthly so like 33% of people chose
monthly even though they saw annual as a
default
on the opposite end the people who saw
monthly there were almost 1100 people
and this was an even split so 1100
people selected monthly so there was
actually a 4.5% increase in people
converting to the monthly so when they
saw the $4 more people did start that
free trial than people who saw $40 in
side note I am using Apple's new pricing
where it is actually just $40 and that's
a whole another experiment I'm actually
running current Curr is the $40 versus
39 we actually running the side by sides
I'm that's my second experiment cont
we're have great content in 2024 because
David I I don't have enough traffic
right now somebody help me out let's get
some
traffic start driving some ads or
something I don't know yeah but anyway
so was $40 or $4 a month and that's
another thing is I was kind of
experimenting with making the price
differential not quite as attractive but
that's another experiment I'd like to
run is like making the monthly a little
more expensive to drive annual but in
this case I was kind of like I want some
monthly revenue and so I wanted it to
balance out a little bit and so I did
the 40 and four which is not a crazy
deal for annual where typically people
who are pushing annual would make it
like 50% off 60% off to do the annual
because they're trying to get that money
up front so people who saw the monthly
as a default it was 1,00 stuck with the
monthly and only a hundred switch to
annual so way more people who saw annual
switched to monthly and almost no
that's really yeah I mean that's
probably going to wipe out your results
just there because it sounds like the
total number of conversions is similar
it's like 11 1200 something like this
yes yeah yeah yeah yeah oh that's
fascinating so like just priming people
on annual is gonna make a huge
difference that's interesting especially
I mean I wonder I mean relatively 40 is
not the lowest for weather apps but it's
also like some apps are for a year it's
100 so it's already kind of on the low
end but that's really interesting so 10%
more people convert converted on the
monthly Oh you mean on the annual primed
more people converted on monthly no
people who saw the monthly as a default
more of them converted by 10% 10% more
people became subscribers when they saw
$4 versus seeing 40 but and again we can
revisit these numbers actually little
shout out to the community here I'm
actually been sharing charts and the
actual results from this in the subclub
community and there's been a great
discussion on that so if you're not
already on the subclub community
go to chat. sub club.com and then
there's a join link there to join the
community I shared it in the private
area of the community but yeah 10% more
people converted to become subscribers
who saw the $4 instead of the 40 but
still when you start doing the math on
the churn on the monthly and everything
else like I'll probably still end up
making quite a bit less money on the
people who saw monthly and stuck with
monthly because get money up front
versus like giving them 12 opportunities
to tr also also to consider the time
cost of money right that money now is
literally worth more value perspective
right than it is like one question to
both of you guys I guess related to this
is when running an experiment like this
right around a launch is that data not
that it's invalid but isn't that a very
different cohort than the people who for
the vast majority of the time are going
to be finding your app through you're
certainly learning more about the
preferences of an interesting user base
than you are and I would super valuable
especially if you're going for big
launches as your strategy uh because
it's good to know how to optimize those
cohorts but that's going to be different
than a month from now all the people who
are finding your app through just search
and definitely just the volume you
already alluded to it David it's like as
you're running subsequent test your test
that's a very subtle test split I mean
I'm interested that there's any sort of
like perceivable result there and
actually I would love to run it for
longer to see if that disappeared
because you're talking five six percent
like could be noise it was statistically
significant though yeah it would be
interested to run those tests on like
yeah Charlie was saying like run rate
like sort of downloads but you'll have
to take bigger swings because the volume
of people going through that funnel is
gonna be a lot lower so to get
statistical significance you don't want
to be testing like green button Blue
Button you want to be testing like
$1,000 and $3 you know like testing
complet versus this completely different
you're trying to do gradient descent
like a machine learning algorithm trains
right like where you want to just create
tests that are big enough part if you're
trying to determine if it's too cheap or
too high or whatever like the bigger
differences you take they'll be
notionally correct right so like the
bigger swings you take if it's like oh
actually there's a little more value in
the higher side so like maybe don't make
that a or that b your actual number then
like find a new number that's closer and
then test that again as well it's really
awesome DAV that you now have a for a
limited time only no for a limited
amount of effort you got a pay wall set
up that you can remotely configure
especially for a developer like in your
position where like you know you have to
Loop somebody else in and youve got
other bugs and features and things to be
working on like now as the business
oriented partner you can pretty much on
your own be running these experiments
analyzing the data and all of that stuff
and I think it's something that yeah I
didn't even have to talk to Brock to
launch that second experiment I changed
the price on App Store connect I already
had two SKS and so I changed the other
annual skew to
$39.99 I left the existing skew at 40
and I set it all up in Revenue cat to
run this subsequent experiment without
touching code without updating the app
without even talking to Brock actually
did you test it at all like in a sandbox
context or anything like this like no no
just go for it yolo it's good I mean you
should be able to like should be fine
especially if the products were already
approved and everything it's really cool
I think this is one thing on Revenue cat
side that we've just kind of started to
Cobble all these tools together but like
we haven't yet and talk about Revenue
cat thinking about what's a launch for
us right like we've been shipping these
little features for the last year and a
half and when you see them all start to
interplay and play together now like we
have a thing and now it's like having
people go through the whole flow we need
to like spread the word on like how to
run these tests like all inside Revenue
cat how to design plans how to do it all
in one place because I think like you
said David like you never 20 years in or
what however many years the apps were in
you've never done this before and that's
crazy because it works right so I'm
excited to see more and more developers
do this and even developers that were
already doing it doing it easier
focusing on other things things like
this so anyway Revenue cat.com
before we land This Plane is there
anything else with this launch either
things that you're going to try going
forward or were there other failures I
miss that you wanted to cover another
huge failure was just me getting my
expectations up we talk about it on this
podcast about product Channel fit and
all the different things you know it got
mentioned in Tech crunch which is a big
deal and I was in N9 to-5 Mac and Mac
rumors and boy Junior report you know it
got a lot of attention again if the dma
hadn't happened maybe there would have
been a little more momentum going but
anytime you're launching an app you got
to think like okay where am I getting
attention and then what's the overlap of
the attention I'm getting and my ideal
customer profile and then the reality is
no matter how much you want to convince
yourself otherwise is that of those
maybe 30,000 people across all the
different press mentions I got let's say
30,000 people's 100,000 people probably
all the headline oh another weather app
I don't care even if they are
potentially even my like ideal customer
profile they already have three weather
app subscriptions and they don't even
get past the headline because they just
don't even care and then they see the
app and they see the video they see
whatever and it just whittles it down
further and further and further and so
like the real overlap of people who are
actually care enough to go click a link
and go buy my stupid little app is so
small that even when you can get a lot
of attention again if that attention
isn't a huge overlap of your ideal
customer profile it's just not going to
be as impactful as you think and so back
to maybe the this whole strategy is
played out unless you're apple and are
launching these massive consumer
friendly apps that genuinely everybody
is part of your potential customer base
then it's not going to be as impactful
as you would hope and assume it would be
so another big lesson I think maybe the
thing there is it's unreliable not
necessarily unimpactful cuz sometimes
you can have like I limped along an
update for iOS 17 to get interactive
widgets for my app and it just so
happened that for whatever reason
editorial picked it to be in one of
their lists and it was the first one in
the list and that was just massively
impactful right and I've had other ones
where I've even gotten on lists but it
was lower down or it wasn't one that
they pushed as hard or whatever reason
and it didn't have those numbers if you
keep swinging on those some of them will
be hits and some of them won't you just
got to launch over and over right you
got to launch over and over launch
launch somebody should make a podcast
with that name yeah some should have a
podcast about
launching a great idea yeah for those
who don't know Charlie runs a podcast
called launched where he talked mostly
to Indie developers about launching and
running their app businesses but yeah I
have it in the notes like where do I go
from here it's launch get feedback
iterate update get feedback launch from
here it's ship ship ship and then keep
doing these experiments and keep trying
new things keep taking swings and
there's the episode title we don't do
that for this one do we but it should be
ship ship ship all right well David it
was a pleasure having you on your own
podcast thank you for joining yourself
where can people find you and your work
I think we should plug Charlie's work I
think like where can people find you
Charlie Revenue cat.com I write articles
on the blog no I I'm on all the
different social media things most
places it's Charlie M Chapman on Twitter
which is what I will still call it it
isore Chuck eec I think is my handle
there and then I have an app called Dark
noise which is a White Noise app which
provides lots of fodder for good Reven
cat content as well as a we'll have you
on after a failed launch yeah perfect
perfect to make it and I guess David you
don't really plug contrast so it's
contrast. co right is where you can find
all your apps yep and the links of
course will all be in the show notes and
I'm actually not the one who has to put
them there so I'm excited about
that it's nice but yeah anybody else
willing to share stories of failed
launches and failed product updates and
screw-ups and everything else get in
touch David rat.com I want to hear more
stories like this hopefully I broke the
ice a little being really open and
honest about some of my failures with
this launch and the thing is like the
story is not written right like we
talked about this launch was a
disappointment but there's still a huge
opportunity and hey I got close to 2,000
people to pay 40 bucks a year for my
stupid little weather I don't know where
the failed came your head David at all I
think that's an unqualified dub in my
mind so all right well super fun talking
to you guys thanks for uh having me on
thank
you thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub
[Music]